[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Five]
[第五集]
The roots of popularising science and democracy
普及科学与民主
lie in education.
根子在教育
If you, Cai Yuanpei,
你蔡元培
can use the treasure of Peking University to reform and innovate
要是能借北大这块宝地改革创新
in order to revive our Chinese nation,
重振我中华民族
you will have our support and hope.
就有了依托和希望
The words of Brother Botang
伯棠兄之所言
are exactly what I, Cai Yuanpei, want.
正是蔡元培我之心志
Okay, I'm going to reply to Li Yuanhong
好的 我这就去回复黎元洪
to take up his post at Peking University as soon as possible.
尽快到北大走马上任
Hold on, Brother Jiemin.
孑民兄且慢
If you want this job, you have to do it right.
这任要上 这谱也得摆
Without water, it's hard to build a canal.
水不到渠难成
If you want to be in this hornet's nest of Peking University,
要想在北大这块是非之地
and make a career out of it.
干出一番事业
It's going to take a lot of work!
非得动一番心机不可呀
Please teach me, Brother Botang.
请伯棠兄教我
I know you have a well-developed idea
我知道你在革新教育上
of how to revolutionize education,
有一套成熟的想法
but in order to achieve your ambition,
但是要想实现你的志向
you have to meet the conditions set by Li Yuanhong:
必须要黎元洪满足你开出的条件
sufficient funds,
经费充足
abundance of talented people,
人才济济
transfer of power to lower level.
权力下放
Without these three demands,
如果没有这三条
no matter how good your plans are
你那图纸就是设计得再好
as the old Beijing saying goes
也应了老北京的一句话
it will be "a blind waste of time".
瞎耽误工夫
With Brother Botang's help, I, Yuanpei,
有伯棠兄给元培我运筹
am certain to become the president of Peking University.
北大校长 我当定了
Good.
好
Excellent, excellent!
太好了 太好了
[Yadong Library, Shanghai]
[上海亚东图书馆]
The young are promising!
后生可畏
This Hu Shizhi fired eight bombshells at once,
这胡适之一下发了八颗炮弹
each hitting the lifeblood of old literature.
颗颗命中旧文学的命门啊
Baisha, hurry up and arrange
白沙 赶紧赶排
the official 1917 New Year's publication
一九一七年一月一日正式刊出
[Yi Baisha, styled Yuecun, scholar of the New Culture Movement] [Wang Mengzou, manager of Yadong Library]
[易白沙 字 越邨 新文化运动学者] [汪孟邹 亚东图书馆经理]
of "New Youth" to China
《新青年》 要给中国
[Chen Duxiu, styled Zhongfu, editor-in-chief of "New Youth"]
[陈独秀 字 仲甫 《新青年》主编]
as a New Year's gift.
献上一份新年大礼
Zhongfu, take it easy, don't rush.
仲甫 你先别急别急啊
Didn't we agree?
咱不是说好了吗
The first issue will publish Hu Shi's eight vernacular poems.
第一期要发表胡适的八篇白话诗
You can't make it a special issue.
你不能弄成他的专刊吧
Besides, he's a nobody,
而且他现在没名
few people in China know him.
全中国没什么人知道他
If he does not sell, we can not afford the loss.
他万一要是不买账 咱可赔不起
Put the vernacular poem further back.
白话诗往后放
This article "A Preliminary Discussion of Language Reform" is more influential.
还是这篇《文学改良刍议》 有影响
Wait, why has it changed to "Reform?"
什么变成改良了
Isn't it a revolution?
不是革命吗
This carries a lot less weight.
这一下分量可差了好多啊
Is this kid scared?
这小子是不是怕了
It's understandable that young people have their worries.
青年人有顾虑可以理解
If he wants "Reform" so be it.
改良就改良吧
I'll write him an editor's note on this one,
这一篇我给他写一篇编者按
and I'll write the "On Literary Revolution" on the next one.
下一篇我来写 《文学革命论》
Yes, the New Culture Movement's
对 新文化运动
flag-bearer
打大旗的
should be a famous person like you, Chen Zhongfu.
还得是你陈仲甫这样的名流
It's enough for the younger generation
适之他后生
to just lead the charge.
打个冲锋就行了
Mengzou.
孟邹
This "New Youth" is becoming more and more influential
这《新青年》 越来越有影响力
and the distribution must keep up.
这发行得跟得上啊
Especially in schools and in some big cities
特别是学校和一些大城市
that have to become our main battlefield.
那要成为我们主要的阵地
I was just about to discuss the prospectus with you.
我正要跟你商量一下招股的事呢
Beijing has a lot of cultural businessmen,
北京啊好多文化商人
who are very optimistic about "New Youth".
非常看好《新青年》
and about you, Chen Duxiu,
也非常看好你陈独秀
and they all wanted to actively invest in the venture.
都想积极地投股
We must go to Beijing in the near future.
最近我们得去趟北京
Good, I'd love to check it out.
好啊 我正想去看看呢
If the New Culture Movement is not active in Beijing,
新文化运动北京要是不动
could it be even called a movement?
叫什么运动啊
If no one in Beijing shows up to support "New Youth",
《新青年》 要是北京没人捧场
does it have any influence?
那算什么影响力呀
I think this can not be delayed.
我看这事不能拖
Next week, next week we will leave.
下周啊 下周我们就动身啊
Next week?
下周啊
Next week.
下周
Alright, alright.
好好好 好
"New Youth"!
《新青年》
Read the newly published "New Youth"!
看刚出版的《新青年》
Read "New Youth"!
看《新青年》了
"New Youth"!
《新青年》
Newly published "New Youth"!
刚出版的《新青年》
You go back first.
你先回去吧
What does this mean?
什么意思
Count it. Two dollars and eighty-six cents.
你数数 两块八毛六
We dried out the magazines.
杂志我们已经晾干了
No need for this.
这个不用了
You still don't want?
你还不要
How about this?
那这样行不行
Count me in to buy thirteen of your magazines.
算我买你十三本杂志
Sold.
买行啊
Qiaonian.
乔年
Wrap thirteen magazines for this sister.
给姐姐包上十三本杂志
That's right!
这就对了嘛
Actually I had a big fight with my dad
其实那天我在家
that day at home.
跟我爸大吵了一架
When I got up in the morning,
我早上起来啊
there was no one at home.
家里一个人都没有了
I was late when no one asked me to go to school.
没人叫我上学 我就迟到了
So I was in a bad mood that day.
所以我那天心情特别不好
My attitude was naturally bad.
态度自然就不好了
So I kicked you all out in a rage.
所以一气之下把你们都轰出去了
Don't take it personally.
你们别往心里
We made mistakes before
我们做错在先
not knowing the school rules.
不知道学校的规矩
I also changed your bucket of water.
还换了你一桶水
We both apologize to you.
我们俩给你道个歉
Don't take it to heart.
你别往心里去啊
Then we will not take it to heart.
那我们都别往心里去
We're even.
我们扯平了
Even.
扯平了
So what you are saying is
那您的意思是
you would like me to go to America with Liu Mei.
让我和柳眉一起去美国
Correct.
对呀
And for your brother,
还有你弟弟
if you agree,
如果你同意的话
I'll ask Mr. Wu Zhihui
我就请吴稚晖先生
to apply for your quotas in the Ministry of Education.
到教育部为你们申请名额
But we can't accept other people's funding.
但是我们不能接受别人的资助
You misunderstood this.
这个你误会了
I'm not trying to fund you.
我不是要资助你
I want you to do me a favor.
我是要你给我帮一个忙
Liu Mei is my only daughter.
柳眉是我唯一的女儿
She is still young now
她现在年纪还小
and has poor ability to live independently.
独立生活的能力很差
If she goes to study alone,
如果她一个人漂洋过海去读书
I won't feel at ease.
我心里不放心哪
But if you go with her,
可是 你们如果跟她一起去的话
you will take care of each other.
互相之间会有一个照顾
I'll be relieved.
这我就放心了呀
And as far as the current situation is concerned,
而且 就目前形势来看
studying in the United States is the best choice.
去美国留学是最佳的选择
This is for you both,
这个对你们
I think, a good thing.
我觉得 应该是一件好事吧
Uncle, I have my own principles.
叔叔 我有我自己的原则
We cannot accept this kindness of yours.
您的这个好意我们不能接受
Farewell for now.
先告辞了
Yannian.
延年
Don't answer me so hastily.
你不要这么匆忙地就答复我
You have to think about it.
你要好好想一想
But remember,
但是你记住
this road I've paved for you,
我给你们铺的这条路
it is definitely wide,
一定是宽广的
it is definitely flat,
一定是平坦的
it is definitely full of sunlight.
一定是充满阳光的
Uncle.
叔叔
I can reply to you now.
我现在就可以回复您
We will walk our own road.
我们自己的路 自己走
Brother Jiemin, please!
孑民兄 快请
[Ministry of Education, Republic of China]
[中华民国教育部]
I missed you so much.
想死我了
Jingsheng!
静生啊
I'm forunate to have you as a friend looking out for me.
我亏得有你这个朋友想着我
Otherwise,
要不然呢
I wouldn't have been able to come back to Beijing.
我还回不了北京
To welcome you, Brother Jiemin,
孑民兄 为了迎接你
[Cai Yuanpei, styled Jiemin]
[蔡元培 字 孑民]
I specially prepared a Red Daughter (brand of speciality wine).
我特意准备了上好的女儿红
[Fan Yuanlian, styled Jingsheng, Minister of Education]
[范源濂 字 静生 教育总长]
Tonight, let's get drunk.
晚上咱们就一醉方休
Jingsheng, let's get down to business.
静生 我们还是先谈正事吧
Don't get drunk later and delay business.
别待会儿喝醉了 耽误正事
OK, then let's get down to business.
行 那就先议正事
Brother Jiemin, Li Yuanhong has made up his mind
孑民兄 黎元洪决心已下
to invite you to join Peking University.
请你入主北大
Six hundred dollars a month.
月薪六百大洋
What do you think? When will you take office?
你看 何时上任呢
As far as I know,
据我所知呢
the enthusiasm of the capital's academic community for the return of Brother Jiemin
这京城学界盼子民兄归来的热情
[Tang Erhe, President of Beijing Medical College]
[汤尔和 北京医专校长]
has never been higher!
空前高涨啊
Don't let down
您可别辜负了
the kindness of Brother Jingsheng.
静生兄的这番好心哪
Yesterday, someone set off firecrackers in North Square of Peking University,
昨天有人在北大北广场放鞭炮
[Shen Yinmo, Professor at Peking University]
[沈尹默 北京大学教授]
reportedly to "Welcome President Cai"!
说是欢迎蔡校长
To tell the truth,
实话实说啊
I've repeatedly weighted the pros and cons before coming
来之前我也权衡再三
and listened to the views of many people.
也听取了多方的意见
The fact I am in Beijing should make my true feelings self-evident.
今天能到北京来心迹不辩自明
I don't need to say too many of these polite words.
这些客套话我也不用多说了
It's that, Jingsheng,
就是静生啊
if President Li approves of my prelminary agreement,
如果黎大总统准了我的约法三章
then I'll be the president of Peking University.
那北京大学的校长我就去当了
Brother, please tell me about your rules.
老兄请讲 哪约法三章
This is my entire vision.
这是我的全部的设想
Please let me show it to you.
请给您过目
Brother Jiemin.
孑民兄
Well, this precedent you're setting is a bit too ambitious.
这 你这口子有点开得太大吧
What's wrong, Jingsheng?
怎么了 静生
It scares the hell out of you?
这就把你吓坏了
And this is just my initial vision for the school.
这还只是我对学校的初步设想
The second planning scheme of the school...
学校的第二套规划方案
Wait, wait, wait.
等等 等等
Brother Jiemin, just the first stage, recruiting talent...
孑民兄 就这一条招揽人才
You want to, from at home and abroad,
你要从国内外
recruit a hundred professors.
自主聘请百名教授
Arts and sciences director, monthly salary of three hundred silver dollars.
文科学长 月薪三百大洋
Other professors range from one hundred and twenty to two hundred and eighty.
其他教授一百二到两百八不等
How much does it cost to pay the head fee for a year?
这一年下来光人头费得多少钱
It is equivalent to dozens of times the current Peking University.
相当于现在北大的几十倍呀
You're demanding a pound of flesh from President Li.
你这不是要挖黎大总统的肉吗
Jingsheng, national modernisation
静生啊 国家要现代
must be education-oriented.
必须教育为主
This is a prerequisite for financial security,
经费保障这是先决条件
You did not recall me to the country
你总不会万里招招把我召回国来
to Peking University to be a business-as-usual president.
到北大去当个维持会长
Is this the original intention of President Li?
这难道是黎大总统的原意吗
Such a big country
这么大的国家
would not be short of this funding for Peking University, would it?
不差北大这几块大洋吧
Minister Fan,
范总长
just talk to President Li.
您就好好地和黎大总统说说呗
Fine. Then I'll go to Li Yuanhong.
行 那我就去找黎元洪
Good. Jingsheng, my regards.
好 静生 拜托了
[Qianmen Chinese-Western Hotel, Beijing]
[北京前门中西旅舍]
Zhongfu.
仲甫
You should listen to me.
你还是听我的
Open a suite for youself.
给你开一间套房
You can't be too shabby when you're talking to people.
你跟人谈事不能太寒酸
No need to put up a show.
不用摆谱
Just a single room is enough.
就单间就行
The people coming to talk about investment are cultured.
来谈投资的都是文化人
They wouldn't pay attention to this.
不看重这个
Just save as much as you can.
能省就省点
You two be careful, here it is.
二位小心啊 在这儿呢
No. The people at the foot of the emperor
不行 这天子脚下的人啊
are all concerned about the show.
都是讲究排场的
I can't let you,
我可不能让你这个
the famous Chen Duxiu of China, lose face.
名冠中华的陈独秀丢了面子
Buddy,
伙计
Give us a suite.
给我们开一间套房
No need, no need.
不用不用
Listen to me, just two single rooms.
听我的 就两个单间
What are you talking about?
讲什么排场啊
If he thinks I'm poor, I won't let him join the business.
他要嫌我穷我还不让他入股呢
Brother Mengzou, no need to be fussy about accommodations.
孟邹兄 这住不用讲究
But good food is a must.
吃一定要吃好
Buddy,
伙计
you say,
您说
Are there any good
这附近有什么
mutton hotpot restaurants around here
好的涮羊肉的馆子吗
that you can recommend?
你向我们引荐一下
Yes, right around the corner.
有 这出了门就是
But at this time, it's all for the rickshaw pullers.
不过这时候都是力巴车夫的专场
You two look like respectable people.
您二位一看就是体面人
Here, you take a few more steps.
这样 您多走几步
Not far to the north is Dong Lai Shun.
北边儿不远啊 就是东来顺
Okay, let's try Dong Lai Shun.
行 那咱就东来顺吧
No need, no need.
不用不用
Just here is fine,
就门口挺好
eating with rickshaw pullers. How fragrant!
跟车夫一块涮 香
Inside please.
里边请
Come! Eat and see! Drink and see!
各位来 吃看啊 喝看啊
Eat and see!
吃看啊
Eat!
吃
Come, eat!
来 吃
Hurry up and eat!
赶紧吃啊
Hurry up, eat!
赶紧吃
Please come in, gentlemen.
二位客官里边请
Come, come.
来来来
Zhongfu.
仲甫
Change the place, change the place.
换个地儿 换个地儿
Right here, right here. It's good.
就这儿 就这儿 挺好的
How lively!
多热闹啊
Come on, come on, are there any seats left?
来来来 还有位置吗
There are, there are.
有有有
Here, sit down. Sit here.
来 您坐着啊 坐这儿
I'm sorry, but this is the only hot pot.
真对不住啊 就这一个火锅了
Can you see if you can talk to this brother
您看能不能跟这位大哥
to use it?
一起合着用啊
How to use it?
合着 怎么用啊
You see?
您瞧着啊
One side of the pot for each, well-water doesn't mix with river water.
这一边一家 井水不犯河水
Well-water doesn't mix with river water, we'll each mind our own affairs.
井水不犯河水
But, is this soup still one pot of soup?
不是 这汤还是一锅汤啊
Yes, it's one pot of soup.
没错 就是一锅汤
Come on, come on. Sit, sit, sit.
来吧来吧 坐坐坐
Two plates of lamb, one plate of tripe,
两盘羊肉 一盘毛肚
chinese cabbage, frozen tofu,
大白菜 冻豆腐
rice noodles, sugar and garlic.
粉丝 糖蒜 全上
You'll see
您就瞧好吧
how lively this is.
这多热闹啊这
Well-water doesn't mix with river water!
还井水不犯河水
It's still one pot of soup.
还是一锅汤
That's right.
就是嘛
Sir, your seasoning is here!
先生 您的调料来啦 来
Thank you.
谢谢啊
This old Beijing lamb.
这老北京涮肉啊
This seasoning is the most delicate.
这调料最是讲究
Sesame sauce, soy beans, curd chives.
芝麻酱 酱豆腐 韭菜花
All essential.
必不可少的
And scallions, coriander and chili oil.
还有葱花 香菜和辣椒油
You have to mix it up.
你得把它拌开
This lamb also has an art to it.
这涮也有讲究
For the tripe, you can't leave the chopsticks still.
毛肚 不能离开筷子
Just seven or eight strokes is enough.
就七八下就够了
Seven, seven...
七 七
If you don't do that, it'll be overdone.
你那个要不就 就老了
Too tough to eat.
吃不动了
This meat should go a few slices at a time
这肉也是几片几片下
into the broth.
汤清
You two take your time, I'm going to do some work.
您二位慢用 我拉活去了
Master.
师傅
Let's go.
走了啊
Take care!
慢走啊
You go!
你走啊
Come on, one more!
来 再划一个
One more!
再划一个
This is the old Beijing way of eating.
人家这才是老北京的吃法
The method that you talked about,
你刚才说那方法
was invented by you
都是被你们这些酸文人
pedantic literary people.
给改了样儿了
Who invented it?
谁改的
We've gained some real first-hand experience.
还真是长了见识了
It's a guest!
上客了啊
Boss!
老板
Interesting.
有意思
It's okay!
可以了啊
Come!
来
Junior!
小二
Two seats?
二位
Two seats, two seats.
两位两位
Okay, please come inside. Come, come, come. This way.
好 里边请 来来来 这边这边
They are still eating.
他们还正在吃
Alright, alright.
好好好
This way!
这边啊
Good.
好嘞
Xingang!
心刚
Mr. Zhongfu!
仲甫先生
Hello sir.
先生好
What a coincidence!
这么巧啊
Why are you in Beijing?
你们怎么在北京呢
After Shanghai,
上海一别之后
we both came to Beijing to study.
我们俩就来北京求学了
Sit down. Sit down.
快坐下 坐下
She had just passed the Peking University entrance exam,
这不 刚刚考上北京大学
But now Peking University doesn't accept female students.
但是现在北大不收女学生
So Bailan worked as a tutor in Dongjiaominxiang
所以白兰在东交民巷当家教
tutoring French at the same time,
同时补习法语
to work and study in France in the future.
以后准备去法国勤工俭学
Today, she just got paid.
今天啊 她刚领了薪水
The two of us planned to come here to have a nice meal.
我们俩就来这儿打打牙祭
I didn't expect to meet you, sir.
没想到碰见先生您了
What a coincidence!
真够巧的
You are at Peking University now.
你现在在北大呀
I wanted a chance to visit Peking University anyway.
我正想有机会去北大看看呢
You can show me around when you have time.
等有时间 你带我去转转
Of course, sir.
好啊好啊先生
You don't know it,
您不知道
but you're a celebrity at Peking University.
您是我们现在北大的名人啊
Many students and teachers are all reading
您办的那个 《新青年》
that "New Youth" magazine you founded.
很多老师跟学生都在读
So admirable!
太佩服您了
Server!
伙计
Coming!
来了
Remove the hotpot separator.
来 把我们这隔板撤了吧
We'll eat from the same pot.
我们是一拨的
Sure.
好
And add another two plates of mutton.
再上两盘羊肉
Will do.
成成成
Anyone can tell at a glance that you're birds of a feather,
一看就是一家人哪
dipping your food next to each other.
涮着涮着涮到一块去了
Have a nice meal.
慢吃啊
Yes.
好
Here, eat.
来吧 来 吃
Go ahead, eat.
动筷 吃
Thank you, sir.
谢谢先生
Eat.
来吃
Zhongfu,
仲甫
You've frightened the kids.
你把孩子们都着了
Mr. Zhongfu,
仲甫先生
have you not eaten for several days?
您有好几天没吃饭了吧
This is a method I've just learned from the labouring masses.
我是刚刚跟劳苦大众学的方法
It's exceptionally delightful.
特痛快
An absolute delight!
痛快 痛快
Hurry up and eat. Gotta pick up a fare.
赶紧吃 吃完拉活去
What fare?
拉什么活啊
Are you pulling a rickshaw?
拉洋车去
Pulling in investors! Hurry.
拉股 快动筷动筷
Alright!
好
Brother Jiemin,
子民兄
from today on, you will be the principal of Peking University.
从今日起 您就是北大校长了
Master Cai,
蔡公
this is a heavy responsibility to shoulder.
北大校长 重任在肩
Please.
拜托了
Jingsheng, this is hard to come by.
静生 得来不易
I will cherish it.
我定当倍加珍惜
I thank everyone for their help.
感谢诸位鼎力相助
I, Yuanpei, will certainly fulfill the mission.
元培 一定不辱使命
Master Cai, when do you plan to assume office?
蔡公 你打算何时上任
And where will you start?
又从何入手呢
It is for you to decide when.
何时上任的时间由你定
And as for where to start,
从何入手
I think the first step
我想第一个要做的
is to recruit talent.
就是网罗人才
First of all, those from the liberal arts.
首先是文科人才
I would like to find someone
我想找一位
who can raise the banner of innovation to be the dean of liberal arts.
能够树得起革新大旗的文科学长
Everyone present, please help me think
诸位替我想一想
who is able to take on this important task.
谁能担此重任
This liberal arts dean
这个文科学长
must be sympathetic to you,
既要能与你蔡元培志同道合
but also be of noble character and high prestige.
还要德高望重
Must be a learned academic,
既要有学术影响
but also with the ability to charge through enemy lines.
还要能够冲锋陷阵
Such a person is not easy to find.
这个人不好找啊
I've thought of someone.
我倒是想起一个人
Chen Zhongfu, or Chen Duxiu.
陈仲甫 陈独秀
This is a person who is leading the trends of today's China.
这可是引领当今中国潮流的人物
He is certain to be able to take on this important task.
他定能担此重任
I also thought of Chen Duxiu.
我也想到陈独秀
Are you know Chen Duxiu well?
你们和陈独秀熟悉吗
Only as an acquaintance.
只是认识而已
But I've read every issue
不过他创办的《新青年》
of his magazine "New Youth."
我倒是期期在读
Yes, his magazine "New Youth."
是 他《新青年》
I also read it.
我也是看了
Brother Zhongfu and I are old friends.
仲甫兄和我是老交情了
Qian Xuantong said that
听钱玄同说
Chen Duxiu has come to Beijing.
陈独秀来北京了
He's asked for a meeting to commission an article.
约他见面向他约稿呢
Where is he living? Do you know?
他住哪儿 知道吗
I will ask around.
我去问问
Yes. Please.
好 拜托
Zhongfu, listen to me. Zhongfu.
仲甫 你听我说 仲甫
That's one hundred thousand shares acquired in one go.
这一下子就搞来了十万的股金
Zhongfu.
仲甫
It's great. Several hundred thousand shares.
太好了 十几万的股金呢
We've done it this time.
这回行了
This time, we can go all out.
这回我们就可以大干一场了
It seems like in Beijing our "New Youth"
看来我们《新青年》 在北京
has a lot of influence.
很有影响力
That's for sure.
那当然
Huge potential market.
市场的潜力巨大
Definitely.
那没错啊
Now I believe the words you spoke last year.
我现在相信你去年说的那句话了
Which words?
哪句话
You said, give you ten years.
你说 给你十年时间
And you will change the thinking of our compatriots.
你将国人的思想都为之改变
Now it looks like it won't take ten years.
现在看来 用不上十年
We must set up a banquet.
不行 我们得摆一桌酒席
To celebrate.
来庆贺一下
Yes.
好
I will ask Xingang and Bailan to come.
我去把心刚 白兰都叫来啊
Quickly.
快去
Yes.
好
Dropped a seed and sprouted a shoot.
丢下一粒籽 发了一颗芽
What branch, what leaf, what flower will bloom?
么杆子么叶 开的什么花
Bear what kind of fruit? Grind -
结的什么籽 磨的什么
Brother Jiemin.
子民兄
Brother Zhongfu.
仲甫兄
How did you find me here?
您怎么找到这儿了
I will always be able to find you.
我总能找到你
Come this way, sir.
快 先生 来来来
Please come inside.
先生 屋里请
In here.
进进进
Please sit, sir.
先生 请坐
Alright. Please sit.
好好好 你坐你坐
Have a seat.
快坐
Yes.
好的
Sir, sit.
坐 先生
Brother Zhongfu.
仲甫兄啊
I have the impression...
我好像记得
that I am a few years your senior.
我 我要年长你几岁
I was born in the year of the rabbit，
我属兔
in the fifth year of the reign of Emperor Guangxu (1879)
光绪己卯年生
We have the same zodiac sign.
我们一个属相
I was born in the sixth year of the reign of Emperor Tongzhi. (1867)
我是同治丁卯年生
You see, I remembered I am a cycle older than you.
你看 我是记得我要大你一轮哪
Do you still remember when we were in Shanghai twenty years ago?
你还记得十二年前我们在上海
Together on an assassination squad,
一起参加暗杀团
prototyping a bomb?
试制炸弹的事情
How could I forget?
怎么会不记得
Couldn't manufacture it, narrowly escaped with our lives.
炸弹没制成 险些送了命
Even now, I often see it in my dreams.
我到现在还经常梦见
True, true.
是是是
At the time, if you hadn't given that shove...
当时啊 要没你那么一推呀
I would not be sitting in front of you today.
我今日岂能在你面前坐着
Dead as a doornail, long ago.
早就完蛋喽
Brother Zhongfu,
仲甫兄啊
you saved my life.
你是我的救命恩人
I have to properly thank you.
我得好好谢谢你
You're too kind. You're overstating it.
哪里哪里 先生言重了
Twelve years ago,
十二年前
I was the age you are now.
我也就是你现在这个岁数
At that time,
那个时候啊
there was nothing I was afraid of doing, nothing I was afraid of saying.
无事不敢做 无话不敢讲
I was brave and unyielding.
人呢也血性得很
But now I am old.
可是现在老了
No longer have that edge.
那棱角没了
And not as driven as times gone by.
冲劲呢 也不如昔日
You're not doing so bad.
你不错
Nowadays, you, Chen Duxiu,
现如今你陈独秀
has raised in China the two big banners
在中国树起了科学民主
of science and democracy.
这两面大旗
And what have you brought the country?
给这个国家带来了什么
A breath of fresh air.
一股清新的空气
I read every issue of your magazine "New Youth."
你的《新青年》我是期期都阅读
With each reading, there's always something to be gained.
每看必有收益
Sir, if you would like to submit a manuscript,
先生若能为《 《新青年》赐稿
I would be extremely grateful.
我定当感激不尽
That is a matter of course. Naturally I will contribute.
这是分内的事 我理当效力
I came here today
我今天来呢
to ask you for some help.
是想请你帮忙啊
Please go on, sir.
先生请讲
Starting yesterday, I have been
我呢 于作日啊
formally appointed the president of Peking Univesity.
正式被任命为北京大学校长
Take a look. Letter of appointment.
你看看 委任状
Congratulations, sir.
恭贺先生
I would like you to come to Peking University to be the Dean of Liberal Arts.
我想请你到北大担任文科学长
Lend me a hand.
助我一臂之力
Lend Peking University a hand.
助北大一臂之力
I hope Brother Zhongfu would not decline.
望仲甫兄切莫推辞啊
I would like to thank Brother Jiemin for the support.
多谢子民兄提携
But this is very sudden.
只是这事出突然
I'm not mentally prepared.
我毫无思想准备啊
Zhongfu,
仲甫啊
the Dean of Liberal Arts is equivalent to the Deputy President of Peking University,
这文科学长相当于北大的副校长
leading the various disciplines of the humanities and social science.
统领文学和社会科学各个门类
Aren't you currently advocating and calling for
你现在不是正是提倡和号召
democratic science?
民主科学吗
I think this would be your best stage to do so.
我在想 这是你最好的舞台呀
Precisely because it's a serious responsibility,
正是因为责任重大
I don't want to rashly accept an appointment.
所以我才不敢贸然领命
After all, I haven't properly gone to university.
我毕竟没有正经读过大学
And have no experience teaching or educating others.
也没有过教书育人的经历
An incompetent person who pretends to be competent
这滥竿充数
will only hinder the progress of their students.
岩不误人子弟
If I actually got in the way of your grand undertaking,
若真是耽误了老兄你的宏伟大业
there would be no greater crime.
那罪莫大鴦了
Don't decline in such a rush.
你呀 你先不要急于推辞
It's true that this is very abrupt.
这个事情也确实来得突然
You can discuss this at your leisure
你可以和家人 朋友
with friends and family and then make a decision.
从容商量 再做决断
I am indeed eager in my search for talent.
我呢 的确是求贤心切呀
I am determined to invite you
我是一心一意请你
to Peking University and work together.
在北大我们一起共事
For China. For education in China.
为中国 为中国的教育做点事
For Master Cai to show such high regard for me,
蔡公如此抬举小弟
I am truly moved to tears.
我真是感激涕零
If Peking University is to become China's highest educational institution,
北京大学 乃中国最高学府
it will be the best platform to advocate for science and democracy.
是弘扬科学与民主最好的舞台
If there is an opportunity to follow Brother Jiemin
若是能有机会追随孑民兄
to Peking University and collaborate on this endeavour,
在北大共做一番事业
it would be the blessing of three lifetimes, exactly what I've been looking for.
三生有幸 求之不得
But to be quite honest,
可是我实不相满
in my heart,
我这心里
I can't let go of my "New Youth."
真的放不下我的《新青年》
This magazine is still a fledgling
这本杂志还是草创阶段
that has just started picking up.
刚刚有了一点起色
I came to Beijing this time
我这次到北京
precisely because of the magazine. Looking for investors and resources.
就是为了它 募资招股
A successful harvest.
大获成功
Only just today, I've discussed
今日刚刚谈了
an investment of over a hundred thousand shares.
一笔十几万的股金
At a time like this,
您说这个时候
if I leave "New Youth" behind without a care
我丢下《新青年》 不管
to take a position at Peking University,
去北大上任
wouldn't I be letting down
那怎么能对得起
everyone's deep regard?
各方人士的厚爱呢
It's true. I understand.
是啊是啊 我明白了 明白了
What you are saying is not without reason.
仲甫兄说得也不无道理
If the result of you coming to Peking University
如果说让你来北大
is the stoppage of the publication of "New Youth."
结果让《新青年》 停刊了
That's unacceptable.
那是不行的
Alright. I will now hurry back
好 我现在就赶紧回去
to discuss how to solve the problem of "New Youth."
去商量解决《新青年》 的问题
Zhongfu, my thinking is this.
仲甫啊我是这样想
Peking University must exist. "New Youth" must keep running.
北大要来 《新青年》 要办
I will definitely find a way to satisfy both requirements.
我一定会找个两全其美的方法
Alright. I'm leaving.
好我走了
Brother Jiemin.
子民兄
Brother Zhongfu.
仲甫兄啊
Let's just call today my first of three humble visits to plead my case.
今天就算我一顾茅庐吧
Ok. I will get going.
好 我走了
Brother Mengzou,
孟邹兄
I beg of you to handle the matter of signing the contracts.
签约的事情就拜托你了啊
I have nothing to say to those business men.
我跟那些商人无话可说
I would only get in the way.
去了也是别扭
What? What do you mean?
不是 什么意思
You're not going?
你不去了
Zhongfu, everyone is coming to see you.
仲甫 大家可是冲你来的呀
Signing the contract is such an important thing.
签约这么大的事
If you don't show up, how will I explain it to them?
你不去 我跟大家怎么解释
Just say I have an important meeting.
你就说我有重要约会嘛
And it's the truth.
再说也是事实
I need to go to Taoran Pavilion to see Quan Xuantong.
我要去陶然亭见钱玄同
You're a really strange person.
你说你这个人啊 真是奇怪
It's snowing so hard.
这外边下着大雪
And it's so cold.
这么冷的天
What are you doing meeting someone at Taoran Pavilion?
你约人到陶然亭去干什么去
To sample the northwesterly wind?
喝西北风去
You don't understand.
这你就不懂了
Heavy snow is romantic.
下大雪才浪漫嘛
This is the difference between a reader of books and a seller of books.
这就是读书人和卖书人的区别
To make joy amidst misery is the essence of a scholar.
苦中作乐 才是士的本质
Not many people these days can keep in tune with such highbrow sentiments.
这年头啊 阳春白雪和者盖寡
I surmise
我断定
Master Qian will not be singing the same tune.
钱大公子不会买你那账的啊
And I surmise
我也敢断定
at this very moment Qian Xuantong is already on his way there.
此时钱玄同一定已经在路上了
Zhongfu. Zhongfu.
仲甫 仲甫
Don't, Zhongfu.
别别别 仲甫
No, if you leave, what do I do?
不 你走了我怎么办
Brother Zhongfu!
仲甫兄
Deqian, is that you?
德潜 是你吗
I've been looking forward to meeting you. Your reputation preceeds you.
久仰大名 如雷贯耳啊
Today, I finally see your face in person.
今日总算是得识真颜了
Myriad entities have different forms, but they are the same in essence.
万物玄同 相忘于道
Though in the corners of the world, we have never met,
你我虽天南地北 从未谋面
we have long since been alike in spirit.
却神交已久啊
This is true.
是啊
[Qian Xuantong, styled Deqian: Peking University professor]
我可是《新青年》 的忠实读者
and a die-hard supporter of you, Chen Duxiu.
也是你陈仲甫的铁杆支持者呀
Deqian, you are too modest.
德潜 你过谦了啊
How is it?
怎么样
To meet at Taoran pavilion in the snow today.
今日我约这雪中陶然亭相见
You don't find it odd?
不觉得奇怪吧
To see Taoran in the snow?
雪中游陶然
'Elegant' is the only word for it.
要的就是一个雅
How can it be odd?
怎么会怪呢
You don't find it cold?
那不觉得冷吗
To meet brother Zhongfu is to be bathed in spring wind.
与仲甫兄相见 如沐春风
Any chill is entirely absent.
寒意全无
We are indeed fellow travellers.
果然是同道中人
We have another fellow traveller.
同道中人还有一位
Let me introduce you.
我给你介绍
This is Liu Bannong.
这位 刘半农
Literary translator.
文学翻译家
and famed writer of the "Mandarin Ducks and Butterflies" school of fiction.
也是上海著名的鸳鸯蝴蝶派报人
Bannong,
半农
I've read many of your translations of European fiction.
我看过你翻译的很多欧洲小说
It has benefited me a great deal.
受益得很
Compared to you, sir,
与先生相比
I am but a handful of soil next to Mount Tai.
半农不过就是泰山上的一抔土
Why are the people in Beijing
这待在北京的人
all so modest?
怎么都这么谦虚呀
Brother Zhongfu, let's talk in the pavilion.
仲甫兄 咱们亭上说话
Certainly.
好来
Speaking of Taoran Pavilion,
这陶然亭啊
among the most famous of its associations
要说最有名的
is the composition by Jiang Zao, "Taoran Pavilion."
当属江藻撰写的《陶然吟》
Reportedly, he often invited
据说他经常请这些
scholars and literati, colleagues and close friends
文人墨客 同僚好友
to come here to feast and compose poetry.
来此饮宴 赋诗
Sure enough, it's a peaceful world in the world of mortals.
果然是 红尘中的清净世界呀
It's a pity, wine is left out today!
可惜今日无酒啊
Brother Zhongfu has come, how can there be no wine?
仲甫兄前来 岩能无酒
Someone come! Bring wine!
来人 上酒
Come, come.
来 来
This wine is Shaoxing yellow wine.
这酒可是花雕
That's right. My hometown's Shaoxing yellow wine.
没错 我老家的花雕
After it's heated up, use a quilt to wrap it.
烫好了用棉被包裹着
It's sent over by a rickshaw.
黄包车送来的
Deqian, Bannong, you guys really used your heart.
德潜 半农 你们可真用心
I'm moved, I'm moved.
感动 感动
I'm waiting for my yellow daisies at home to ripen.
更待菊黄家酿熟
We'll get drunk together and have a good time.
共君一醉一陶然
Good! Today there's you, there's snow,
好 今日有你 有雪
there's Shaoxing yellow wine, there's a qin, there's poetry, there's red plums.
有花雕 有琴 有诗 有红梅
Having intimate friends in high mountains and rivers. It is indeed elegant.
高山流水觅知音 果然雅致
Come.
来
Let us first toast a cup.
咱先干一杯
How is it?
怎么样
Warm!
暖
Come.
来
Banong, weren't you at Shanghai?
半农 你不是在上海吗
How come you also came to Beijing?
怎么也到北京了
Is it to keep up with the latest fashion?
是赶时馨吗
Peking University is making reforms.
北大搞改革
I was thinking of coming over to apply for a teaching job.
我是想过来应聘教书
Is this Beijing so attractive
这北京对文化人
to cultural people?
就这么有吸引力吗
It's strange to say that
说来也怪啊
at present, these scholars,
眼下这些文人驿客们
once arrived, won't leave.
来了就不走
They rush in like ducks,
那是趋之若鹭啊
no matter how poorly they live here.
无论在这里活得多贫穷
Why is that?
为什么
High culture, low culture.
阳春白雪 下里巴人
Dragons and fishes jumbled together, all embracing each other.
鱼龙混杂 包罗万象
The opportunities and risks coexist.
机遇与风险并存
Come.
来
Brother Zhongfu.
仲甫兄
This "New Youth"
这《新青年》
is like the fire of today's winter day.
就像今天这冬日里的一把火
It ignited the light of hope of revitalizing China.
点燃了振兴中华的希望之光
We are all followers of this torch.
我们都是这把火炬的追随者
This time Duxiu comes to Beijing
独秀此次来京
to pay his respects to all of you,
就是要拜竭各位
to help "New Youth"
襄助《新青年》
to make its fire burn brighter.
把这把火烧得更旺些
An unshirkable responsibility.
责无旁贷
Come.
来
Only, Brother Zhongfu, have you thought about
只是仲甫兄 有没有考虑过
Beijing.
北京
Of course.
当然
More than gain a footing,
岂止是立足
to be based in Beijing, we can look at the whole country and develop it.
立足北京 放眼全国 发扬光大
Come, today we are not going home until we're drunk!
来 咱们今天不醉不归
Okay! Cheers. Come.
好 干 来
Excuse me, may I ask
请问一下
Is the guest home?
那客人在家吗
Yes. However, he came home pretty late last night.
在 不过他昨天晚上回来挺晚的
It seems like he drank a little too much.
好像还有点喝多了
I reckon he's still not up at this time.
估计这时候还没起床
Let me call for you
我帮您叫一下
Don't wake him up too loudly.
你不要吵醒他
Let him sleep a while more.
你让他多睡一会儿
Continue.
你忙吧
Alright.
好的
Cabinet minister Cai.
蔡总长
I am Cai Yuanpei.
我是蔡元培
It's really you!
真的是您啊
Y-you, what is this you are doing?
您您 您这是干什么
Zhongfu is resting.
仲甫在休息
I am waiting for him here.
我在这儿等他
How can this be allowed?
这怎么能行呢
How can we allow you to be so condescending to simple men like this?
怎么能够让您这样屈尊降贵呢
I'll call him, I'll call him.
我叫他我叫他
Zhongfu!
仲甫
Don't, don't, don't.
别别别
Don't, don't wake him up.
别 不要叫醒他
Let him sleep a while more.
让他多睡一会儿
I can't, I can't.
不行不行不行
I see that you look very familiar.
我看你这个人很面熟
Cabinet minister Cai, your humble servant Wang Mengzou.
蔡总长
Wang Mengzou... I know.
汪孟邹 我知道
Scholar of Anhui province's Jixi county.
安徽绩溪的秀才
Director of Yadong county's library.
亚东图书馆的经理
That library of yours is taken care of really well.
你那个书馆搞得很好
You overpraise.
您过奖
Zhongfu.
仲甫
Brother Jiemin.
子民兄
I drank too much yesterday.
昨日喝多了
Quick, enter the room.
快屋里请
Come, come, come.
来来来
Enter quickly, don't catch a cold.
赶快进去 别受凉了
Forgive me, forgive me.
失礼失礼
Don't catch a cold.
别受凉了
Forgive me, sir.
失礼了先生
Please sit, sir.
您请坐 先生
You sit, you sit.
你坐 你坐
I'll offer tea to you.
我给您奉茶
You take a seat first.
你先坐着
You guys chat first, I'm going to handle some matters.
你们先聊 我去办点事
Cabinet minister Cai, it was nice to meet you, nice to meet you.
蔡总长 幸会啊幸会
Sir, drink tea.
先生 您用茶
No need, I'm eating peanuts.
不用 我吃花生
Boldly paid a visit, disturbed your rest.
冒味来访 打扰你休息了
Where?
哪里哪里
I just wanted to tell you
我就是想告诉你
Me and Cabinet Minister of Education Fan Yuanlian,
我和范源廉教育总长
as well as colleagues of Peking University,
以及北大的同仁
after the negotiations feel
商议之后认为
you are able to have "New Youth"
你可以把《新青年》
brought to Peking University to manage.
带到北大来办
At the same time,
与此同时
"New Youth" can also
《新青年》 还可以在北大
implement a lecture on editing for colleagues at Peking University.
实行教授同人编辑
If this happens then,
这样一来
"New Youth" can have Peking University
《新青年》 就可以把北大
treated as something to give publicity to Mr. Science and Mr. Democracy,
当作宣传赛先生 德先生
an exceptionally good platform.
绝佳的讲台呀
With this, we will promote and spread the New Culture Movement.
以此来提倡和推广新文化运动
I still need to tell you,
我还要告诉你
the head of humanities course's monthly income is three hundred silver dollars.
文科学长月薪是三百块大洋
Your whole family can go up north,
你可以举家北上
settle down in Beijing.
在北京安家
Make up your mind. Come to Peking University.
下决心吧 来北大吧
I sincerely need your help.
我是真心诚意需要你的帮助
Honorable Cai, inviting me so kindly like this,
蔡公 如此盛情相邀
Duxiu is endlessly grateful.
独秀感激不已
Speaking truthfully, these two days have been a rush of excitement.
说实话 这两天也是然心动
Cannot sleep soundly at night.
夜不能霖
After drinking some wine yesterday night,
昨天晚上喝了一些酒
only then have I felt I had a good sleep.
才睡了一好觉
It's just that, the matter of "New Youth" entering Beijing,
只是这《新青年》 进京一事
its implications are profound.
事关重大
It involves all aspects,
涉及到方方面面
so I don't dare agree rashly.
所以我不敢贸然答应
How about,
要不然
I recommend you someone to be the dean of liberal arts.
我给您推荐一位文科学长吧
For sure, more outstanding than me.
肯定比我出色
But this dean of liberal arts,
但是这个文科学长
how can it be possible for another person to take it?
岂能是他人所承担得了的
Only you can do it.
非你莫属啊
Zhongfu, Zhongfu.
仲甫 仲甫
Please enter.
请进
Zhongfu.
仲甫
Yihan.
一涵
Greetings, sir.
先生好
Sir.
先生
Bailan, Xingang, you're all here.
白兰 心刚你们都来了
Come. Quickly, Come meet Mr. Cai Jiemin.
来 快 来见过蔡子民先生
Honorable Cai, it's an honor to meet you at last.
蔡公 久仰久仰久仰
Greetings, Mr. Jiemin.
子民先生好
Greetings everybody.
大家好
What brings you here?
这什么风把你吹来了
Brother Zhongfu.
仲甫兄
You are able to arrive in Beijing, it's really too good.
你能到北京来真是太好了
Hearing you already arrived in Beijing,
听闻你已经到了北京
Mr. Zhang Shizhao specially sent me a telegram.
章士钊先生专门给我发了电报
Let me be sure to invite you
让我一定要来请您
to our "The Tiger Daily" editing department,
到我们《甲寅日刊》 编辑部
to take a look,
去看一看
and give guidance.
给予指导
If he doesn't invite me, I would go by myself.
他不请我 我也得自己去
"Jiayin" is my old magazine.
《甲寅》 是我的老东家
How come Shouchang didn't come?
守常怎么没来啊
Shouchang isn't here because he's visiting his family.
守常是因为家里面临时来了客人
In a moment, he will
他等一会儿会
directly hurry to the editing department.
直接赶到编辑部去的
Alright, then why don't go over right now.
好啊那咱们现在就过去吧
Brother Jiemin
子民兄
Then... You are--
那 您是
How about you-- Go over together with us.
要不您 跟我们一块过去
It's alright, I'm busy.
不了 你忙
I'll come over again next time.
我下次再来
Okay, okay, okay.
好好好
Mr. Cai, it's really nice to meet you.
蔡先生 真是幸会
You--
您
Brother Zhongfu.
仲甫兄
About the matter of coming to Peking University,
来北大一事
I am still asking you to carefully think it over again.
还敬请您再仔细思量思量
I have been sincere.
我可是二顾茅庐了
These peanuts are really delicious.
这花生很好吃
Take care.
您慢走
Sir. I'll send you.
先生 我送您
Take care, sir.
先生慢走
No need to send me out. I can do it.
你留步 我来
Mr. Cai, walk well.
蔡先生 走好
Come. Please enter, please enter.
来 请进请进
Brother Zhongfu, you're welcome to look around.
仲甫兄 欢迎您参观
"The Tiger Daily" editing department.
《甲寅日刊》 编辑部
This is Mr. Xingyan's great work.
这是行严先生的大手笔呀